today we will be making the vintage
catgan sweater that i've seen a couple
of times
this is based on the sandra miller max
fields design
and i went onto stitchfiddle.com and
recreated this design but with my colors
the main color that i chose is white and
i will be using
four different shades of blue for the
cats and for this pattern
i made four different pieces that i
sewed together in the end
i first made two sleeves and two panels
one
for the front and one for the back that
were identical i used a five millimeter
crochet hook
and a yarn needle to sew in my loose
ends first i'll start with the sleeves
so i'm going to be starting where the
cuff of the sleeve is
to start we'll need a slip knot and to
make a slip knot hold your yarn with the
tail end
at the bottom wrap the top part around
two of your fingers to form an x
use your hook and go under and over and
pull that piece of yarn through
and then remove your fingers and tighten
the knot
then i'm going to chain 11 to chain
yarn over and pull through so again you
just yarn over
and pull through and this will be the
width of the cuff
it goes along your arm not around it
if you want this to be longer or shorter
you can adjust the number of chains that
you do
after i've chained 11 i'm going to half
double crochet
into the second chain from the hook to
half double crochet
yarn over insert your hook into the
second chain
from the hook yarn over pull through
yarn over and pull through all three
loops
again yarn over insert your hook into
the next chain
yarn over pull through yarn over and
pull through
all three loops and now i'll just do
this all the way across into
every single chain until i have a total
of ten half double crochets
once i finished my 10 half double
crochets i'm going to chain one
and then turn and then i'll start
working half double crochets into the
back loops only so you want to yarn over
and then go through the top into the
center of that v
come out the back side and then
yarn over pull through yarn over pull
through
all three loops so we're just doing the
same half double crochets but working
only into the back
loops and once i reach
the end i'm going to chain one turn
and do that same thing over again
and i'm going to be doing the same thing
until it fits
when i wrap it around my wrist
i did a total of 14 rows and now i can
slip stitch the ends together
first we'll go into the front loop of
that first stitch right next to the hook
and then we'll grab the other end and go
over and
into the back loop at the other end
[Music]
and then to complete the slip stitch
yarn over and pull through
and then pull through the loop on the
hook
and again you want to insert your hook
into the front loop
of the next stitch go over and into the
back loop
of the next stitch on the other side
yarn over
pull through and then pull through again
and then we'll just continue this
until we reach the end
once we're finished slip stitching the
cuff close we can chain two
and then start working double crochets
into the side of the ribbing
to double crochet yarn over insert your
hook into
the side of the very first row yarn over
pull through then yarn over and pull
through two
and then yarn over and pull through the
last two so again it's a yarn over
insert your hook into the side of the
first row again yarn over pull through
yarn over pull through two yarn over
pull through two
and then i'm just going to do one more
into the side of the first
row so i will be doing three double
crochets
into the side of each ribbed row for a
total of
42 stitches and you can increase or
decrease this number of stitches
depending on how baggy you want the
sleeve to be
now that i've finished my 42 double
crochets we can slip stitch
and start the next round to slip stitch
insert your hook into the very first
double crochet of this round
so we're going to skip the chain two
that we did and go under
both loops that make the v from our
first double crochet
of this round so again to slip stitch
insert your hook into that stitch
yarn over pull through and pull through
again
and then you want to pull it tight to
make sure that the seam is less visible
now we can chain two and start the next
round
so every round we'll end with the slip
stitch
and start with the chain two and our
very first stitch of this next round
is going to be that same stitch that we
just slip stitched into
and for a total of 32 rounds
i'm just going to be doing one double
crochet into every single stitch
as you work your seam will start to
slant towards the right
and in order to get a straight seam you
can
skip the first stitch in every fourth
round
so this is optional but if you want a
straight seam
then on your fourth round you want to do
your chain two
and instead of going into that same
stitch you just slip stitched into
you want to skip that one go into the
next one
and after you've gone all the way around
you want to
make that first stitch you skipped your
last stitch of the round
so for my last stitch i'm going to
double crochet
over that chain two go into that stitch
and do my double crochet there
[Music]
and then slip stitch and it should move
your seam
back towards the left and again i'm only
doing this
every fourth round
after i've done 32 rounds i'm going to
fasten off
if you want a longer sleeve do more
rounds or
less rounds for a shorter sleeve to
fasten off
chain one and then cut off a strand of
yarn
if you want to use this strand of yarn
to sew your sleeve to your front and
back panels
then you should leave this strand really
long
about three feet or 90 centimeters
should be long enough
[Music]
and then you want to pull on that loop
that your hook was in
and just pull through all of that yarn
we can start working on the front panel
this part started off exactly the same
as the sleeves
i made the ribbing at the bottom of the
sweater the same width
as the cuffs on the sleeves
i started with a slip knot and then i
chained 11
and did 10 half double crochets across
but i continued the ribbing for a total
of 40
rows so this length should be about
the length from one hip to the other
and instead of working in the round
we're going to be making
two of these panels and sewing them
together
once i finished my 40 rows of ribbing
i'm going to turn it so i can start
working along the side
first we'll chain two and then instead
of
three that we did for the sleeve i'm
going to be doing
two per row and this number is important
because it'll give me a total of
80 stitches which is the correct number
for the graph that i'm using
if you want a smaller or larger sweater
then you'd have to adjust this graph
by adding more or less cats
and first it's really important that i
say that
each of these squares represents two
double crochets
because when you do two double crochets
right next to each other it forms
a square so this graph is 40 by 40
squares
but it means 40 rows
and 80 double crochets so we're going to
be starting from the very bottom of the
graph
and working our way up so our very first
row
is just 80 double crochets across
in white so i've just finished the first
row
and i'm going to use a bobby pin to mark
this
as my right side so this is the side
that will be on the outside of the
sweater
and the wrong side the other side i'm
going to
drop all of my yarn and that is where
i'm going to be sewing
all of my loose ends into whenever we're
working with the right side facing up
we're looking at the graph from right to
left
and if it's the wrong side then we're
looking at the graph from left to right
for this next row we're going to be
adding some colors so i'm going to grab
some binder clips to use as bobbins
these really aren't necessary at all
they just help you from
tangling your yarn too much but i do end
up
just giving up on them completely and
just
leaving all of my yarn attached
so if you do want to use something like
this then you can just
start winding your yarn around it
and you just sort of estimate how much
yarn you're going to be
needing for each cat
you want to really make sure that you
actually
want to use these because if you don't
end up giving yourself
enough yarn you're going to end up with
a lot more loose ends to sew in
and now we can start row two which uses
four different colors so first i'll
chain two
and then turn and like i said before we
are now going to be working
from left to right since we are working
on the back side up you can also think
of it this way
since round one is right side up
every odd round will be working from
right to left
and every even we'll be working from
left to right
so starting from left to right there are
two
white squares before i have to change
into
my first color i'm going to call this
color number one
so since there are two squares that
means i need four double crochets before
changing color remember that each square
is two double crochets and before i
finish my fourth one my last one before
the color change i'm not going to pull
through
the last two loops i'm going to leave it
and then grab my first color
and pull through those last two loops
with that first color and this just
provides
a seamless color change and i'm going to
drop my first
colors tail end off onto
the wrong side of the piece and i'm
going to do the same
with my white yarn this just keeps
all of the loose ends on the same side
and just
makes it a lot easier in the end when
you have to sew everything in
and you want to make sure that you leave
the tail end at least a few inches long
so that you can sew them in easily
according to my graph
my first color will be in the next
eight squares which means 16 double
crochets
and in my 16th double crochet i'm going
to
pull through the last two loops into my
next color which is
white again and again i'm going to drop
my
yarn on the wrong side
and continue with the white next
is 14 squares in white which means 28
double crochets
and in my 28th double crochet i'm going
to pull through the last two loops
with color number two again i'm just
dropping all of my yarn
onto the same side and
for color number two there are seven
squares so
14 double crochets
[Music]
and then i'll switch into color number
three and then i'll use this color for
16 more double crochets
and for the final square of this row
we're going to be switching
back to white and doing our last two
double crochets
when we're done with row two we can
chain two
and then turn and now we're back to
working
with the right side up so this is also
an
odd row so we're going to be looking at
the graph
from right to left looking at row number
three
we have two double crochets in white and
then we're switching
to color number three for four double
crochets
and we can just pick up our color number
three
from where we dropped it last row
and you can see that it creates sort of
a line of yarn here
and i'm just going to crochet
under that to hide it but it doesn't
really matter because
it will be on the inside of the sweater
after doing four double crochets in
color number three you want to switch
to the color of yarn for your eyes and
i'm grabbing a new piece of white yarn
that isn't already attached to my
project
and you want to make sure you're
dropping all of the tail ends onto the
wrong side
which is the other side since we're now
working with the right side up
and while i'm doing the eyes i'm going
to hold my color number three yarn
so that i can crochet underneath it and
carry it along
because we're going to be needing that
really soon
[Music]
whenever you carry your yarn you want to
make sure to pull it
tight so it doesn't scrunch up
and poke through so after i do my two
double crochets
in white for the eyes i'm going to
switch
back into color number three and do four
more double crochets
and for this part i didn't carry the
white yarn but i really recommend that
you do
if i were to redo this project then i
would not cut the yarn at this part
i would carry the white yarn like i did
with the blue one just now
by cutting the yarn instead of carrying
it it just causes
too many loose ends that are unnecessary
so after four more double crochets in
color number three
i'm going to switch back to white and do
two more double crochets for the other
eye
and then we'll switch back to blue and
then do four more for the rest of the
cat
after you're done with the second eye
here is where you should cut your yarn
if you carry it over in the middle
you'll end up with two loose ends
instead of the four that i have now
[Music]
then switching back to color number two
we're going to do
10 double crochets in this color and
then switch
to white
this color change is a little bit
different because the colors don't
quite line up nicely and we're going to
have to grab
the white yarn all the way from where we
dropped it from last row and then we'll
pull it through
the last two loops and there is going to
be the strand of yarn
but we can just double crochet over that
and
it'll be hidden so
if that ever happens in the graph then
you can just pull the yarn all the way
through
and just crochet around it
and this is where i leave you until we
get to
a certain part on the graph
so right now i'm in the top left corner
of the graph
and you can see how it changes from
21 to 22 it goes from this green color
to
white and so when you get to that part
you want to change into your white
before you
finish your green color and chain
with your white because the chain will
be showing up
in that next row and you want it to be
that same color
as the rest of that row
for the end of row 22 i carried the
white yarn along
the green
[Music]
and in my last green i switched into
my white because the very next
double crochets will be in white and
while i'm doing the white
i'm also carrying along the green
because there will be a green
square right next to it
[Music]
and then i'll also be carrying the white
again because the white will come
directly
after
now i have finished round 24 and i'm
done using
all of these colors and i will just be
using white for the rest of this front
panel
and i did 10 rows in white after my last
colored round so for rounds 25
to 34 i did just white
[Music]
so after this light blue cat which is
the last cat that i did
in color i did 10 rows of
white and this is where the front panel
comes up to your neck
but without the ribbing for this next
part we are going to be forming the
neckline
and we are going to be double crocheting
across only
part of the way i started this next row
with 25 double crochets
and then i'm going to do eight rows of
25 double crochets
and i'm going to do the same on to the
other side of the panel
to form a hole in the middle
so after i've done 25 double crochets
i'm going to
chain two and then turn
and start working 25 double crochets
for seven more rows for a total of eight
and the length of this is just how low
you want the neckline to be
so if you made it longer then the
neckline would be lower and if you made
it shorter then the neckline will be
higher and once i'm done i'm going to
fasten off
first i'll chain one and then i'm going
to measure out
how much yarn i'll need to sew this part
to the back panel after i've done it and
i just went three times
across the top but i found that you only
really need it
two times across
now we're going to attach our yarn so we
can do the shoulder piece for the other
side of the panel
first you want to make sure that the
last row of double crochets
is facing the other way
and then we're going to count 25
stitches from the left
and in that 25th stitch i'm going to
insert my hook
and i'm going to pull up a loop with my
yarn
make sure to leave a tail end long
enough and then chain
two
and the first double crochet should go
into that same stitch that we
inserted our hook into and then we'll do
double crochets all the way across and
then chain two
and do the same thing for a total of
eight rows
and once we're done we're going to
fasten off with the tail end long enough
to sew
the top of the shoulders together and
you only need to leave a tail
this long for sewing on one of the
panels so for my second one
i won't be needing to leave it this long
now we're done with our first panel and
i'm going to do one
identical to this one for the back panel
if you want the design just on the front
then you can just do the back panel with
all of your base color just make sure
that you have
the same number of rows on each panel
the next step is to sew the tops of the
shoulders together so we can work on the
collar
first you want to lay the panels right
on top of each other
with the right sides facing out
so all of the loose ends are on the
inside
first thread that long piece of yarn
through your yarn needle
and we're going to be doing the whip
stitch into the
outer loops on both panels
so we're going to be going in a sort of
clockwise motion
and we're going to go through the back
and
go through only the back loop of the
back panel
and go over and into the front loop of
the front panel
and then pull all the yarn through make
sure it's taut
and then we're going to go back around
into the back of the next stitch over
and into the front
of the front panel
and pull it taut and just continue going
in that circular motion
and once we're done we just need to tie
a knot to make sure it doesn't come
loose
and since the loose end on the other
panel is already here
we can just double knot it with that
loose end
and we can leave it to sew in later on
otherwise we can tie a double knot
with one of the stitches in the sweater
i usually do this by just going under
one stitch and looping my yarn around
the needle
and then pulling through and that should
make a knot
and then we'll just do this to the other
shoulder
and we can start working on the collar
you typically want to attach your yarn
into the back panel
so that the seam isn't in the front so
for my sweater i don't really have a
back panel so i'm just going to
go into the third stitch from the right
because we are going to be doing a
double crochet
four together in each of these corners
and just insert my hook and loop my yarn
through and then chain two
[Music]
and work a double crochet into that same
stitch that i attached my yarn to
and then i'm going to work double
crochets all the way across
for this middle section
and we're going to go all the way across
but stop at the last two
and now we'll double crochet four
stitches together
for each of the eight rows in the
shoulders i counted it as having
two double crochets per row so to double
crochet four together
yarn over insert your hook into the next
stitch
yarn over pull through yarn over
pull through two and then yarn over
go into the next stitch yarn over pull
through
yarn over pull through two then yarn
over go into the side of the first row
on the shoulder part
yarn over pull through
yarn over pull through two then yarn
over
go into the side of that same row
yarn over pull through yarn over pull
through two
and then we're going to yarn over and
pull through all five loops
on the hook so we basically started
double crochets in the next
three stitches but we finished it in the
fourth stitch
this just combines all four stitches
into one
and creates a curve so that the corners
aren't so
sharp and then we'll just continue doing
two double crochets
per row along the shoulder pieces
and for each of the parts where i reach
the shoulder seam
i will just add one double crochet
[Music]
and before our last row
we are going to do a double crochet four
together again
so again you want to just start your
double crochet
go into the next stitch
and pull through two loops and then
start the next double crochet
go into the side of that same row
and then pull it through two loops start
another double crochet
and we're going to turn and start
working along the middle part
and just pull through two loops and then
finally
do our last double crochet into that
fourth stitch
pull through two loops and then pull
through all five
and we'll just need to do this two more
times until we
reach the end of this round
and here i would be doing my very last
double crochet four together
and once you're done just slip stitch
and then
we're going to start the ribbing so
we're going to be doing the ribbing
while slip stitching it to the sweater
every other round
to start i'm going to chain 11 like i
did for the other ribbed parts of this
sweater
and then i'll do my first half double
crochet into the second chain from the
hook
and then do nine more for the rest of
the chain
[Music]
and now we're going to slip stitch three
together
to do this insert your hook into that
same stitch we slip stitch into
yarn over pull up a loop go into the
next stitch yarn over pull up a loop
go into the next stitch the third one
yarn over pull up a loop and pull that
loop
through the other three loops on your
hook and we'll do that one more time
by pulling up a loop in the next three
stitches
and with that last stitch we're going to
pull
that loop through the other three loops
on the hook
and now we're going to turn and do the
second row of our ribbing
so i'm not going to chain one because we
already slip stitched
up and i'm going to skip those first two
v's that were from my slip stitches
and i'm going to go into the third one
and do
my ten and a half double crochets into
the back loops only
once i get to the end i'm going to chain
one and turn
so normally i turn the other way but
this way we don't have to turn the whole
project
and then i'll work ten more half double
crochets back the other way
and the very last double crochet is a
little bit hard to see and if you have
trouble with this last stitch then you
can just
skip doing the back loops only for the
last one because it doesn't make too
much of a difference
and now is where we're going to slip
stitch three together
two times so we're going into the next
stitch over from the last slip stitch
three together
and we're going to pull up loops in the
next three stitches
and pull that last loop through the
other three loops
and then we'll do this one more time
turn and work
our half double crochets in the back
loops only again
and we'll just continue this pattern all
the way around this entire
neck part
and i had 114 stitches which is a
multiple of three
i'm going to be able to finish with a
perfect
slip stitch three together but it's okay
if you don't you can just slip stitch
two together or just one
but after you've done all of your rib
rows and i did a total of 19
we're going to slip stitch the two ends
together
and we'll be slip stitching from the
outside in but if you ended up on the
other side then you'll go
inside towards the outside and we're
just going to be slip stitching the same
way that we did for the
cuffs of the sleeves
so again we'll just insert our hook into
the front loop of the first piece over
and into the back loop
of the back piece
[Music]
and yarn over pull through and pull
through again
and we'll just slip stitch all the way
across for the 10 stitches that we have
and if there's a hole at the end that
you want to close up then you can just
add another slip stitch
and once we're done we can fasten off by
chaining one
cutting off our yarn
[Music]
pulling it through with our hook and
then using our hook
to go inside the sweater and pulling
that loose
end through to the inside where we can
sew it in
now i'll be showing you my technique for
how i like to weave
my ends in this part is also optional
you can choose to just not weave in your
ends because this will be on the inside
of the sweater
and no one will ever see it but if you
do want to weave in your ends
here is how i like to do it so first of
all
since there are so many colors i'm going
to try to make sure that i weave in my
ends
under the same color so that i don't
have other colors poking through
to demonstrate this i'm going to take
this light blue yarn
in one of the cat's ears first i'll
thread it into my needle
and i'm going to tie a knot with my yarn
needle
so i'll go under one stitch
wrap my yarn around the yarn needle
[Music]
and then pull it through if there was
another loose end
right next to it then i could just
double knot it with that loose end
but since we don't have that then we'll
just tie a knot with itself
the next step is to move it to an area
where there is enough space
horizontally for me to start to weave in
the ends properly
so i'm just going to go under some
stitches with my yarn needle trying to
move
the loose end down and once i get to
that
long horizontal line of blue i can
go under a few of the stitches and pull
it through to the other side
and then i'll turn back around skip one
stitch
and go back under those same stitches
and again i'll turn back around and go
under those same stitches
once again since you're looping the yarn
back and forth in the same directions
if you tug it then it'll be pulled in
those different directions
and it'll be hard to come loose
with the eyes it's hard to weave your
loose ends under the same colors
since there's only two double crochets
per eye
so we'll just have to go under the
colored yarn so i'm doing the same thing
i'm just going under a row of stitches
and i'm checking on the other side to
make sure that the white isn't poking
through too much
and then i'll turn back around and skip
one stitch and go back
under those same stitches
and then i'll go back a third time while
making sure that it's still not poking
through to the
other side and then we can cut the
excess yarn
i'll do this with the rest of my loose
ends and we can start working
on sewing the sleeves and down the sides
of the sweater
the first thing you'll want to do is
align the pieces together
as you can see from the graph the green
cat on the left
should line up with the green cat on the
right knowing this
i'm going to first look at the green cat
with the eyes
and the lowest row for that one should
be one row higher than the other side
so i'll use a bobby pin to pin those two
parts together
and you can also add more bobby pins to
make sure that it is perfectly aligned
[Music]
to sew on the sleeves we'll be using the
same technique that we use to sew the
tops of the shoulders together
first you want to grab your sleeve and
fold it along the seam
and you want to place it so that the
seam goes along the bottom of the arm
and i'm going to be working into the
panels of the sweater
and then into the sleeve i think it's
important to
stay consistent with this because it can
make your seam
look different if you switch it around
for the other sleeve
so after i've threaded the yarn through
my needle
i'm going to go into the side of
the front panel and then into the top
layer of the sleeve
going into the outer loop of that v
of the stitch and then i'll go back
around into the top panel
and then into the outer loop on that
sleeve
and back around to the panel into the
and i'll do this all the way until i
reach the shoulder part
it's important once you get to the
shoulder that you don't make it too
tight
otherwise it'll start to puff out at the
shoulder
so you want to be extra sure that
everything is laying flat
and you're not stitching this part too
tightly after we go
over the shoulder we're going to be
working into the back panel
and into the back of the sleeve
[Music]
and then once we finish sewing down the
back of the sleeve
we can start sewing the side of the
sweater together
and you want to be sewing tightly enough
that there are no holes
but also making sure to line up your
pieces together
properly
and once i got to the green part i
skipped over it and started working
the rest of the white i actually
recommend
that you start a new piece of yarn
because i did end up actually
cutting this in half later on because
i didn't like that you could still see
the white yarn so i just continued
sewing with my white yarn
and once i got to the ribbing i did the
outer loops only again
and then i tied a knot and weaved it in
for the green part i grabbed a piece of
green yarn
and i just started sewing the two pieces
together
and don't forget to tie a knot with both
ends
of this new piece of yarn and that's the
very last thing we have to do
that is all for this video i really hope
you enjoyed it please leave a like if
you did
and subscribe for more thank you so much
for watching i'll see you next time
you